<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pedagogy | Victor H. Souza</title>
    <link>https://vhosouza.github.io/category/pedagogy/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://vhosouza.github.io/category/pedagogy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Pedagogy</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://vhosouza.github.io/media/icon_hu8d7500d2420c0000b894f0459714a4ed_195899_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Pedagogy</title>
      <link>https://vhosouza.github.io/category/pedagogy/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 5: Unfortunately, the end...</title>
      <link>https://vhosouza.github.io/post/t5-end/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vhosouza.github.io/post/t5-end/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a series of blog posts about my learning activities in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.opennetworkedlearning.se/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Open Networked Learning&lt;/a&gt; (ONL202) pedagogical course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TL;DR&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reflections on the ONL course. The course content is the course. Online learning can be fun, interactive and bind people. Knowledge is acquired in different forms, from group work to reflections posted in the blog.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Online Networked Learning course has come to an end. It has been a great journey with intense group and individual work. It was intense, took considerable effort and time, but didn&amp;rsquo;t feel so. ONL was amazingly well organized with a diverse set of engaging activities. In the middle of the course I even asked myself, what am I learning here? What is the focus? When I realized that the course content and learning outcomes was right in front of me, as the course itself, I got really excited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were all there to learn about opennes, sharing, collaborative and network learning, online course design, and digital literacy in teaching. Every topic transition was smooth and seemed pretty well interconnected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quick summary of the main topics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Online participation &amp;amp; digital literacies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open Learning - sharing and opennes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning in communities - network collaborative learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design for online and blended learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which basically covered:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Digital literacy enables you to map your knowledge and use of digital tools, useful when creating and managing online courses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you create an online course, think about openning and sharing, you may get useful reviews, comments and critiques&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Online learning benefits from creating a community of strongly connected people, building a community and network connections promote learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Different frameworks and models have been postulated when designing an online course, raising the importance of scaffolding students, thinking about social, cognitive, and teaching presences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would probably change the order that topics are presented, as below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Online participation &amp;amp; digital literacies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design for online and blended learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning in communities - network collaborative learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open Learning - sharing and opennes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Course design is one of the most important topics, but came on a period that students were already stuffed with work. I felt that, in general, people engaged a bit less in this topic than the preceding ones. So, I would like to have first the discussions on digital literacy, then study about the course design models, then address the learning in communities to finally reflect on open learning by sharing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, the group work was amazing. Through the PBL activities and follwing the FISh model really promoted an interactive and collaborative work. I realized that with approapriate design and methods it is possible to have fun and fruitful online activities in group. In my next course, I&amp;rsquo;ll certainly promote these activities and implement most of the principles I learning in the ONL. These need to be done slowly as they require more effort from the teacher, and trying to implement all at one may overwhel me, as a teacher, and the students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once more, I would like to thank all my colleagues from the PBL group &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, through which I learned so much, had lots of fun and am grateful to be part of it. Thanks Mohit, Kinaz, Marcus, Stephanie, Hui-Chen, Erik, and Vigdis, with the great guidance by Charlotta and Cecilia. 😄&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Group 6 members:&lt;/strong&gt; Victor Souza, Mohit Gupta, Kinaz Al Aytouni, Marcus Stensmyr, Stephanie Birkner, Hui-Chen, Erik Elfgren, Vigdis Ahnfelt, Charlotta Hilli, and Cecilia Hellekant.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 4: Design for online and blended learning</title>
      <link>https://vhosouza.github.io/post/t4-blended-design/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vhosouza.github.io/post/t4-blended-design/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a series of blog posts about my learning activities in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.opennetworkedlearning.se/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Open Networked Learning&lt;/a&gt; (ONL202) pedagogical course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TL;DR&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blended (in-class + online) learning opens up a new set of oportunities to engage and motivate the students. Students should sense ownership of their learning path. Teacher supports with clear instructions, fostering learning in a flexible environment. Check out the main models for desiging blended courses.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;blended-learning&#34;&gt;Blended learning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s topic is about methods to support course design in Blended Learning. A first question that comes up is: &lt;em&gt;What is blended learning?&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blended learning is combining online and in-classroom activities to expose students to different types of learning methods. The blended learning is an interesting concept because of the greater selection of tools that can be employed to engage students. Our current teaching challanges due to the pandemic restrictions also push the development of such blended activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teaching in hard sciences, e.g., physics and computer science, can greately benefit from blended learning. However, most of higher education institutions are still mostly delivering content in the traditional lecture style. However, these fields have the great advantage of dealing with problem solving cases, which can be augment by online tools. The use of online activities may raise the interest of the students and motivate them to engage more with the course activities. This is only succesfully achieved, if the teacher provides scaffolding through constant check ups and clear instructions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The clear set of instructions and norms are possibly the most important thing to consider when desiging a blended course. Students can easily get overwhelmed in an online environment with the plethora of information. In flexible learning environment, the student motivation can significantly decay if the learning path is not well-defined and possibly lose the sense of purpose. In the topic below, I listed three models worth checking to assist in designing a blended course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;frameworks-and-models-for-blended-learning&#34;&gt;Frameworks and models for blended learning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, our PBL group &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; prepared a compass rose point to different directions each representing a framework or model to support designing a blended course. We highlighted the:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blogs.ucl.ac.uk/abc-ld/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ABC Arena for Blended Learning&lt;/a&gt;: Designed at the University College London, it provides a well-structured model with step-by-step instructions on how to quickly adapt the teaching activities to online mode.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gillysalmon.com/five-stage-model.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The 5 stage model&lt;/a&gt;: Provides a structured development process that supports the construction of better online learning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://oasis.col.org/handle/11599/3095&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Community of Inquiry&lt;/a&gt;: Introduces a framework to create a home for a community escaping from the conventional teaching styles and is based on engaging students to create paths and explore what they want to learn, taking a more flexible approach to learning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below, you will find a snapshot of our Compass Rose work, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://miro.com/app/board/o9J_ldwqE2k=/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; you can access the interactive board we built.&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-learning-in-communitieshttpsmirocomappboardo9j_ldwqe2k&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;[Learning in communities](https://miro.com/app/board/o9J_ldwqE2k=/)&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/t4-blended-design/compass-rose-learning_hu82058f3339dadd06fd0fb0ac9edc4400_150632_f24ccef84508764443bc12d4368a5696.webp 400w,
               /post/t4-blended-design/compass-rose-learning_hu82058f3339dadd06fd0fb0ac9edc4400_150632_b723cc81a10ce2bc58c2bd43f7e0e941.webp 760w,
               /post/t4-blended-design/compass-rose-learning_hu82058f3339dadd06fd0fb0ac9edc4400_150632_1200x1200_fit_q90_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://vhosouza.github.io/post/t4-blended-design/compass-rose-learning_hu82058f3339dadd06fd0fb0ac9edc4400_150632_f24ccef84508764443bc12d4368a5696.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;396&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;a href=&#34;https://miro.com/app/board/o9J_ldwqE2k=/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Learning in communities&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Group 6 members:&lt;/strong&gt; Victor Souza, Mohit Gupta, Kinaz Al Aytouni, Marcus Stensmyr, Stephanie Birkner, Hui-Chen, Erik Elfgren, Vigdis Ahnfelt, Charlotta Hilli, and Cecilia Hellekant.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 3: Learning in communities – networked collaborative learning</title>
      <link>https://vhosouza.github.io/post/t3-collab-coop/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vhosouza.github.io/post/t3-collab-coop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a series of blog posts about my learning activities in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.opennetworkedlearning.se/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Open Networked Learning&lt;/a&gt; (ONL202) pedagogical course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TL;DR&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning in communities is different than network learning. Both types have important contributions to the development of knolwedge in higher education.
Teachers should account for each student characteristics and design group activities that foster a collaborative work. PBL groups and interdependent assements are great starting points.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;collaborative-x-network-learning&#34;&gt;Collaborative x network learning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a great challenge in current higher education in achieving collaborative learning. In most cases, group activies are designed in a way that the level of engagement between students vary considerably. In online courses, the situation is even more critical as digital literacy may hinder some student&amp;rsquo;s participation. In this context, teachers play an important role in designing the courses and activities to foster a collaborative and active participation of the students, promoting learning in communities through joint, fun steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pedagogical training provided at Aalto University has been an eye-opening for the benefits of network and collaborative learning. Especifically, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.opennetworkedlearning.se/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ONL202&lt;/a&gt; activities have demonstrated the feasibility of real collaborative learning through the problem based learning (&lt;strong&gt;PBL&lt;/strong&gt;) groups led by two facilitators. The interesting feature about ONL202 is we construct our knowledge based on the experiences shared by our teammates and through the process of accomplishing the necessary tasks. We not only support the work of our colleagues (&lt;u&gt;cooperation&lt;/u&gt;) but we also build together (&lt;u&gt;collaboration&lt;/u&gt;) solutions to common learning problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working in a research group in a University, my Personal Learning Network is strongly populated with my work peers. Luckily, I also have strong learning connections with my parents and relatives. Both my parents and many of my close relatives are teachers, which created in my childhood an environment based on learning activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One special link that is part of anyone&amp;rsquo;s learning network is the internet. Nowadays, the new standard is to learn through the myriad of content, e.g., videos, blogs, openly available in the internet. Therefore, technological advances and the building up of social networks have enabled the expansions of our own personal learning network beyond our daily circle. Looking from outside, openness and sharing are the pillars of network learning in current society. But it&amp;rsquo;s important to note that collaborative activies are necessary in higher education. For the differences between collaborative and network learning, check the slide below prepared by our PBL group &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-learning-in-communitieshttpsdocsgooglecompresentationd1nwemuoftu__mfg5w5zkisf_r3cluvtdwp0u0njqiqtyedituspsharing&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;[Learning in communities](https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1nwEmUoFtU__mFg5W5zkIsF_r3CLuVtDwP0u0njQiQTY/edit?usp=sharing)&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/t3-collab-coop/diff-network-community_hucf9649b6d163c10adaea5b93f042eba2_94042_e64feed1734a1efcf93da4bb9f65013b.webp 400w,
               /post/t3-collab-coop/diff-network-community_hucf9649b6d163c10adaea5b93f042eba2_94042_0931e444941ee100758c90ea9432bbe3.webp 760w,
               /post/t3-collab-coop/diff-network-community_hucf9649b6d163c10adaea5b93f042eba2_94042_1200x1200_fit_q90_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://vhosouza.github.io/post/t3-collab-coop/diff-network-community_hucf9649b6d163c10adaea5b93f042eba2_94042_e64feed1734a1efcf93da4bb9f65013b.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;428&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1nwEmUoFtU__mFg5W5zkIsF_r3CLuVtDwP0u0njQiQTY/edit?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Learning in communities&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;towards-collaborative-learning&#34;&gt;Towards collaborative learning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We (PBL group &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) prepared a few slides with some relevant tips for designing courses to encourage students to collaborate, work in groups, and a few strategies to support teachers when implementing collaborative learning. Feel free to take a look at it &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1nwEmUoFtU__mFg5W5zkIsF_r3CLuVtDwP0u0njQiQTY/edit?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Group 6 members:&lt;/strong&gt; Victor Souza, Mohit Gupta, Kinaz Al Aytouni, Marcus Stensmyr, Stephanie Birkner, Hui-Chen, Erik Elfgren, Vigdis Ahnfelt, Charlotta Hilli, and Cecilia Hellekant.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 2: Open Education</title>
      <link>https://vhosouza.github.io/post/t2-open-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vhosouza.github.io/post/t2-open-education/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a series of blog posts about my learning activities in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.opennetworkedlearning.se/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Open Networked Learning&lt;/a&gt; (ONL202) pedagogical course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TL;DR&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open education is key in providing accessibility to learning. There are many online tools and local oportunities to start being an open teacher. The benefits of open education can reach beyond the expected. Yet, barriers exist and should be considered down the road to openness.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today we talk about open education. During the ONL course activities, my first impression was that attending teachers and students were mostly concerned about the barriers and dangers in becoming &lt;em&gt;open&lt;/em&gt;, while the benefits and impacts were hindered. Open education is paramount in providing accessibility to education resourses for those who could not access it before. To raise awareness about the possible benefits in promoting Open Education, I prepared an introductory video that you can check below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/d7hqpVW2AMc&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-road-to-open-education&#34;&gt;The road to Open Education&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our (PBL group &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) prepared a presentation to introduce the road to Open Education for someone interested in joining this endeavour. You can navigate through &lt;a href=&#34;https://prezi.com/view/IsV78cBtrhSEGa3rMX2a/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the road&lt;/a&gt; from the &lt;strong&gt;Start&lt;/strong&gt;, where we gathered some useful tools that can be used to prepare and make available open courses. It&amp;rsquo;s very important to remember that this is a joint effort between the teacher and the institution. Openning a course can be time consuming and requires &lt;strong&gt;strong support&lt;/strong&gt; from colleagues, admnistration, and staff. On the path to openness, additional care should be taken with copyrights, ethical and privacy issues, and so on. Nonetheless, the ultimate benefits and impacts might manifest as a more inclusive and equal society, promote personal development and critical thinking, and lastly create a community of people that share and exchange knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-the-road-to-open-educationhttpsprezicomviewisv78cbtrhsega3rmx2a&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;[The road to open education](https://prezi.com/view/IsV78cBtrhSEGa3rMX2a/)&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/t2-open-education/road_open_ed_hudfdf1710a36f450865ed16a2a4edfe53_1490884_cd436ba7c667a2ff36168b1075c44e97.webp 400w,
               /post/t2-open-education/road_open_ed_hudfdf1710a36f450865ed16a2a4edfe53_1490884_43bc2e42259d46a8d4e5f70a7724940b.webp 760w,
               /post/t2-open-education/road_open_ed_hudfdf1710a36f450865ed16a2a4edfe53_1490884_1200x1200_fit_q90_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://vhosouza.github.io/post/t2-open-education/road_open_ed_hudfdf1710a36f450865ed16a2a4edfe53_1490884_cd436ba7c667a2ff36168b1075c44e97.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;424&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;a href=&#34;https://prezi.com/view/IsV78cBtrhSEGa3rMX2a/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The road to open education&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few interesting scientific publications about Open Education&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.14742/ajet.4252&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bozkurt et. al (2019) &lt;em&gt;An analysis of peer reviewed publications on openness in education in half a century: Trends and patterns in the open hemisphere&lt;/em&gt;, Australasian Journal of Educational Technology, v.35&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.6087/kcse.97&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Seo et al. (2017) &lt;em&gt;Equality, equity, and reality of open access on scholarly information&lt;/em&gt;, Science Editing, v.4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sbspro.2016.07.094&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Khalid et. al (2016) &lt;em&gt;Digital Exclusion in Higher Education Contexts: A Systematic Literature Review&lt;/em&gt;, Procedia - Social and Behavioral Sciences, v.228&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Group 6 members:&lt;/strong&gt; Victor Souza, Mohit Gupta, Kinaz Al Aytouni, Marcus Stensmyr, Stephanie Birkner, Hui-Chen, Erik Elfgren, Vigdis Ahnfelt, Charlotta Hilli, and Cecilia Hellekant.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic 1: Online Participation &amp; Digital Literacy</title>
      <link>https://vhosouza.github.io/post/t1-digital-literacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vhosouza.github.io/post/t1-digital-literacy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a series of blog posts about my learning activities in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.opennetworkedlearning.se/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Open Networked Learning&lt;/a&gt; (ONL202) pedagogical course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are living in an exciting era with high demand for teaching digitalization. I hope that my posts will bring useful information for everyone interested in pedagogy and online learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TL;DR&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Online learning opens the possibility for teaching methods that address each individual needs, but requires an appropriate knowledge for a successful implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The visitor and resident map is a good first activity to illustrate personal online engagement;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use inclusive tools, provide clear instructions;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Account for all types of inteligence. People learn differently also in the online environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be prepared to swictch roles with students, many are native in technology.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digitalization opens many new possibilities to improve teaching and learning in multiple levels. Teachers are now capable of providing more diverse, accessible practices that suit well each kind of intelligence and social background. However, fostering online participation and engagement with online tools requires that both teachers and students are reasonably comfortable and literate in digital technologies. These requirements are potentially dangerous in segregating those students with limited online access and may also bring more stress and additional load to the teachers to handle. &lt;strong&gt;Here, I discuss a few points to assist teachers on making better use of the digital environment to foster better learning practices.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-the-visitor-and-residents-map&#34;&gt;1. The visitor and residents map&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David White presented the interesting &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital_Visitor_and_Resident&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Visitor and Resident&lt;/a&gt; framework to map how we engage with different digital tools. In this chart, one drafts a two-axis chart with Visitor and Resident on the limits of the X axis and Personal and Work on the limits of the Y axis. Then, the person is free to place any number of digital tools (e.g., e-mail, office software, YouTube, blogs) in the chart to illustrate how he/she considers to use these tools in the personal and work context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The visitor and resident map can be quite useful for a teacher as a breaking-the-ice activity in the begining of a course, to get to know better the students&amp;rsquo; engagement with the online world, and subsequently tailor the learning activities accordingly. In the video below, David White makes an elegant and quick introduction to the Vistor and Resident model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/sPOG3iThmRI&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-multiple-intelligences&#34;&gt;2. Multiple intelligences&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We, human beings, exhibit a diverse set of intelligences, which are nicely described by Howard Gardner&amp;rsquo;s work on multiple intelligence and education (&lt;a href=&#34;#references&#34;&gt;Smith, Mark K.; 2002, 2008&lt;/a&gt;). Teachers should be aware that each student may learn through different means. Gardner&amp;rsquo;s theory propose the following multiple intelligences:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Linguistic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logical-mathematical&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Musical&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bodily-kinesthetic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Saptial&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interpersonal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intrapersonal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could add another type of intelligence, the &lt;strong&gt;Digital intelligence&lt;/strong&gt;, which shapes how we absorb information, interact, and create knowledge through digital means. Childrens and adolescentes have been already exposed through their whole lifes to digital technologies, in the form of games, online activities, and social interactions. In this scenario, the digital world creates a novel intelligence that also contributes to how we learn through digital means. Putting yourself in the younger&amp;rsquo;s perspective, you will probably realize that it&amp;rsquo;s getting harder to think how can we learn something if we can&amp;rsquo;t search or interact with it online. You can navigate through our &lt;a href=&#34;https://miro.com/app/board/o9J_ktd8SVw=/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Miro board&lt;/a&gt; to explore the content we created.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-online-engagement-how-to-improve-it&#34;&gt;3. Online engagement: How to improve it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a group effort, we (Group 6&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) created the DigiLit Fish (figure below) as a diagram with questions and answers (recommendations) on how to improve the online participation and student engagement in the digital learning spaces.&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-the-digilit-fish-by-group-6-onl202httpsmirocomappboardo9j_ktd8svw&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;[The DigiLit Fish by Group 6 ONL202](https://miro.com/app/board/o9J_ktd8SVw=/)&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/t1-digital-literacy/digilit_fish_hu7b62577adf0573e3a571618bde5344e0_463813_1f29304dc710cb11bffc21c4fb50a029.webp 400w,
               /post/t1-digital-literacy/digilit_fish_hu7b62577adf0573e3a571618bde5344e0_463813_4714ed84f34c1e037714acb3ae315c58.webp 760w,
               /post/t1-digital-literacy/digilit_fish_hu7b62577adf0573e3a571618bde5344e0_463813_1200x1200_fit_q90_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://vhosouza.github.io/post/t1-digital-literacy/digilit_fish_hu7b62577adf0573e3a571618bde5344e0_463813_1f29304dc710cb11bffc21c4fb50a029.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;460&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;a href=&#34;https://miro.com/app/board/o9J_ktd8SVw=/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The DigiLit Fish by Group 6 ONL202&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Promoting online engagement is a difficult task that requires full consideration of the cultural background, tools, and participants&amp;rsquo; roles (teachers and students) (&lt;a href=&#34;#references&#34;&gt;Yengin et al., 2010&lt;/a&gt;). Cultural and social background defines several aspects of the digital literacy. For example, different than in classical lectures, in online teaching the students might know better how to use digital tools than the teachers, switching the role with the teacher. Teachers should be prepared to benefit from this situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The selected tools for teaching should be clearly introduced and selected to promote inclusion of every student, considering possible access limitations and how they operate as &lt;a href=&#34;#1-the-visitor-and-residents-map&#34;&gt;visitors or residents&lt;/a&gt;. There are a plethora of webpages that compiled available free online tools for teaching, for instance &lt;a href=&#34;https://opensource.com/article/20/4/open-source-remote-teaching-tools&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://elearningindustry.com/321-free-tools-for-teachers-free-educational-technology&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We may assume that students can easily adapt to novel technologies, however, clear training and instructions would possibly contribute to a more efficient learning and online engagement (&lt;a href=&#34;#references&#34;&gt;Ozdamar-Keskin et al., 2015&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-the-online-engagement-diagram&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The online engagement diagram&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/t1-digital-literacy/diagram_hu3a36459ad376d5217e3c2267f2c9e236_124286_856f37311be1e57dcb57e24c90cc9b69.webp 400w,
               /post/t1-digital-literacy/diagram_hu3a36459ad376d5217e3c2267f2c9e236_124286_be32a10f51b585de6933133b36c3394b.webp 760w,
               /post/t1-digital-literacy/diagram_hu3a36459ad376d5217e3c2267f2c9e236_124286_1200x1200_fit_q90_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://vhosouza.github.io/post/t1-digital-literacy/diagram_hu3a36459ad376d5217e3c2267f2c9e236_124286_856f37311be1e57dcb57e24c90cc9b69.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;538&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      The online engagement diagram
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://files.eric.ed.gov/fulltext/EJ1105611.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ozdamar-Keskin et al. (2015) &lt;em&gt;Examining Digital Literacy Competences and Learning Habits of Open and Distance Learners&lt;/em&gt;, Contemporary Educational Technology, v.6 pages 74-90.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.infed.org/mobi/howard-gardner-multiple-intelligences-and-education&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Smith, Mark K. (2002, 2008) &lt;em&gt;Howard Gardner and multiple intelligences&lt;/em&gt;, The encyclopedia of pedagogy and informal education.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sbspro.2010.03.942&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Yengin et al. (2010) &lt;em&gt;Roles of teachers in e-learning: How to engage students &amp;amp; how to get free e-learning and the future&lt;/em&gt;, Procedia - Social and Behavioral Sciences, v.2 pages 5775-87.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Group 6 members:&lt;/strong&gt; Victor Souza, Mohit Gupta, Kinaz Al Aytouni, Marcus Stensmyr, Stephanie Birkner, Hui-Chen, Erik Elfgren, Vigdis Ahnfelt, Charlotta Hilli, and Cecilia Hellekant.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
